um I was wondering if we could talk
about anich once
again it's been a while
yeah and I found some sutas pointed out by
and I found some sutas pointed out by
another
friend which shows where the how to
develop or where that perception of a
naturee should be developed how it
should be developed what's the
importance of
it it says because there are these three
things the view of
satisfaction the view of self and wrong
View and these other three things are to
be developed for abandoning those three
things mhm the perception of
impermanence mhm is to be developed for
abandoning abandoning the view of
satisfaction so that's the perception a nature CH is
so that's the perception a nature CH is
to be developed to abandon the view that
things are satisfying yeah yeah so I
have a view that this is satisfying my
situation it's great I like you know my
my body is good it's working it's I'm
satisfied my life my family my views my
convictions are satisfying to me
yeah that's why like when as this other
s to say like you know when SAS in
Brahmin live withdrawn from sensuality
physically but then they start falling
into views like really start holding the
views because that becomes where they
find their safety and
satisfaction and comfort in their
convictions um
so yeah you could see like what we said
that before I think obviously in many
other talks um anicha uh needs to be
can only be understood on that personal
level so when you find things that are
dear to you and contemplate their
sensation or change the feeling that you
get as a result of it well that's the
closest to an N you can get in the
beginning and that's the direction to go
but the problem is obviously with like a
you know contemporary Buddhism the whole
kind of mass of commentaries and like a
scholarly interpretation of
terminologies and so on that's not paid
with the fundamental practice and the
Right View uh then you get these ideas
of this
scientific um that that things are constantly
um that that things are constantly
changing and that's why they're not real
and that's why duka is not
real but you realize well then the
Buddha would have simply said that he
said everything is constantly changing
and none of your pain is real and
nothing is ever real but he
didn't he said contemplating permanence
to overcome come
satisfaction to abandon satisfaction in
things in Damas in views in
possessions and you could realize
anybody can adopt the view any scientist
who is measuring sort of physicist or
whatever that it's measuring data
measuring things measuring electrons
constantly moving would say oh things
are constantly changing anybody can
develop that view anybody can adopt that
view no prerequisites needed you just
need to hear it and need to be please
about it and that's
it you don't need to endure anything you
don't need to keep the precepts you
don't need to um well you don't need to
abandon uh safety that you find in the
world and all the satisfaction you're
justop the view that everything is
constantly changing and yeah often
people like that people that follow
commentaries and and kind of
contemporary interpretations would often
try and connect and say yes of course
modern science has proven that
everything is constantly changing and
see the Buddha also said that so the
modern science has proven that the
Buddha was right as if such thing is
possible puj can prove an Aran right
that's just insane or so so the whole
the whole idea of like um things
constantly changing and everything is
constant flux and it is linear a leads
to B leads to C leads to D and that's
how everything is going and moving and
one to the next and that's when nothing
is real That's why nothing is
permanent that doesn't require anything
nor would that view uh uproot your
satisfaction in the world it would not
make a difference you would just provide
a a new gloss the latest veneer of of
kind of hindsight interpretation of what
it is but things can never be
experienced like that like if things are
constantly changing second to Second you
would not be self-conscious being there
would be a no steadier reference point
that's not as changing as
much you would simply be s
from A to B and C and there would be no
there would not even be a notion of
memory so the whole point is and see
like again when people adopt that view
although they might draw it from from
science or from
whatever commentary explanation and so
on it's not uh it does not remain just m
intellectual there is the whole kind of
emotional side invested in that because
people would have arrived at the
Buddhist teaching because they want to
be free from suffering but then they
jumped into this view that then as I
said a
retroactively describes what happens to
you which is why nothing is real which
is why you don't
suffer and then they get emotionally
invested in that because they are
suffering well yes because basically
they want to be free from suffering so
they invest in this explanation that
tells them that their suffering is not
real because everything is constantly
changing so it's not going to be easy
for them to then just drop that view
because that means now they have to drop
their whole idea of practice the whole
idea of that kind of relief that they
got from the belief that their suffering
is not
real but that is
necessary if they were to actually start
to understand the endurance because you
know when the Buddha described there is
there is rising is Manifest ceasing is
Manifest and persisting while changing
is manifest the three
characteristics so persisting while
changing means exactly that persisting
as the same thing while changing on a
different level and you realize
everything everything so it's like my
intention to sit here and talk to
you it remains
persisting because if I change my mind
I'll get up and walk
out so all these other things that are
constantly changing my arms are moving
my my mouth is moving I'm speaking
different sounds are coming out
different questions different ideas all
of that is on a lower level so that is
changing while my intention to remain
seated talking to you is not
changing and if you were to say well
that intention to remain seated here and
talk to you well that's just an idea
that's just well it it is an idea it's
an image it's real as such and
furthermore if there isn't not idea in
my mind to sit here and talk to you none
of these smaller things that I do would
be intelligible they would make no sense
because there would be no unifying idea
there would be no idea that persists
while these things within that idea are
changing so that's the whole point then
a person if they were to if they were to
basically overcome their scientific view
of everything is in a constant flux and
changing from A to B to C and that's
nothing is real and it's just empty
Concepts they like from from where they
standing when they hear the the third
characteristic that they would have
talked about persisting while remaining
the same sorry changing while remaining
the same or persisting while changing
depending on
translation uh that would to them feel
like eternity like that's permanent oh
but that's all that's permanent it's
like well yeah so first you have to now
adopt the idea that things are
permanent and see how that
feels and then start seeing okay but
that permanence is not mine it's not for
me it's not I am and that's the closest
that's much closer to the
impermanence that to to actual that puj
can come so it's not about denying
things it's about removing your
satisfaction and sense of safety that's
found in them so ironically enough The
View that everything is constantly
changing moment to moment flux
Consciousness just coming and going
coming and going is obviously a thing
that's not changing their view is is is
is not changing on that level
and that's the that's basically where
they find satisfaction in that
explanation of how things are of what's
happening to me of why my suffering is
not real and if I stick to it all the
concepts will just disappear in my mind
and I will be left with the pure reality
was like well pure reality is just
another concept you just
used and the concepts were never the
problem that's again what the Buddha
said himself as far as the language goes
as far as the words and designations go
that's how far tagata has explained the
dharm there's no issue there's not no
need to say our words are just mere
Concepts there is a real reality which
you just Express through Words which is
a mere concept which means real reality
is just mere Concepts then as well how
can you possibly perceive anything that
would not involve a notion of a concept
of it and he said as far as the
designation goes as far as namarupa goes
as far as the words and language goes
tagata has understood it and explained
it that's it not not less not more than
that if somebody claims that there is
more that they can explain more than
your language can
convey or or less they don't know what
they're talking
about that's not possible he said such
thing is not
possible so if somebody wants to contemplate an
so if somebody wants to contemplate an
exactly
find things experiences in your life
that you are find finding satisfaction
in they're satisfying for
you that you find safety in all of that
and see it real as such there is no
reason to deny it there is no reason to
to to undermine it with these
explanatory views oh but that's not real
because electrons are constantly moving
and and collaps or whatever else no no
no it's really such otherwise you
wouldn't be finding safety in it so
what's the problem then oh the problem
then is when you reflexively recognize
your situation oh I am finding safety
say like the typical example would be
I'm finding safety in my family my
family is my satisfaction things I work
for things I produce things I have that
is my
satisfaction but then if you are honest
and you recognize that your satisfaction
rests upon these things that are
fundamentally not in your
control and then you feel anxiety Then
You Feel The Dread then feel what if I
lose these things oh suffering how do I
free from suffering well you could go
the route of as I said commentarial
ideas they had nothing to do with the
early texts they were introduced much
later of deny the reality of of those
things say your son your daughter
they're not real they're just electrons
and stuff and and and Hammer in that
until you kind of deny any dependence on
it while you're still dependent on it
because no amount of saying it's just
electrons would make you not feel
suffering if you were to lose them there
and then in hindsight then you would explain
then in hindsight then you would explain
that that wasn't suffering it was just
this but first and foremost you will
feel it or go the route that actually
the Buddha said you should go if you
want to prove the suffering recognize
that your satisfaction your safety
depends upon those things that are not
in your control allow that feeling to
endure how can mind endure that feeling
of what if I lose everything that's dear
to me through purification of
virtue so through sense restraint and
virtue your mind becomes stronger and is
able to endure such anxious thoughts and
possibilities and then gets to see them
even the dearest of those things the
dearest of assumptions the dearest of
perceptions that I had have cannot be
owned in and of itself it is Unown mind
doesn't move in face of it Mind Is Not
Afraid from it anymore like what if I
better stop thinking about it I better
either explain that they not real or
distract myself from it no you remain
with those things presently enduring for
you so that pressure those feelings the
anxiety what if I lose things that I
love that remains there and the mind
stops fighting them stops trying to to
to sort of uh deny them or stop stop
trying to look away and then you get to
see well it has aison on its own even
the notion of attachment as such it's
not in my control as such it is
impermanent whatever has come to
be because it's there that is its
impermanence its
manifestation is its Unown
ability cuz you you didn't create things
you just find them presented to you then
you get attached and everything else
sure but all that's secondary to their
manifestation so that's the s's
understanding whatever is of the nature
to
manifest it's because of that
manifestation that it's impermanent not
because I will observe its
ending and that's also another problem
with that whole commentator addition
notion of of of like things constantly
in the Flux Of change means you need to
observe things change things ending to
know the
impermanence but that doesn't apply to
any things of the personal matter how
can you observe your life ending so in
other words if you want understand the
commentarial type of impermanence
you need to die because you're still
alive your life is still here
enduring it's not ending so how can you
then be free from the five Aggregates
and samsara because by that view the
ending means you need to observe it
gone but that's impossible so quite the
opposite Ana does not require things to
disappear it actually requires them to
be
there that's why this soap's
understanding is whatever ever is of the
nature to
manifest that's why it's impermanent not
whatever was on the nature to be here
and it's now gone that's why it's
impermanent no no no whatever is here
because it's here that's why it's unable
that's why it's impermanent it's of of
the nature so actually you should
practice impermanence before things
change and disappear yeah because if you
don't well exactly you won't see it yeah
you you're attached to those things that
you find satisfaction in yeah because
you don't see their nature of being
subject to change subject to change
while not changing that's the point
yeah so you have something that you're
attached to your family whatever your
possessions your view your views yeah
the the satisfaction and safety you get
on account of you that explains how
everything happens how everything ties
in yeah yeah that is again you find
safety in
it and that's why people would hold such
views oh it's this leads to that leads
to that that's why Always people want to
understand things that happened to them
especially things that cause suffering
like I want to know why it happened why
did he say such and such thing why did
she do such and such thing and having to
like having some sort of retroactive
kind of in hindsight extra information
feels like okay I understood it I'm fine
now but as the Buddha said that's
completely wrong way to go about it you
get shot by an arrow instead of trying
to figure out why he shot you what was
his clan what was his reason what did I
do to him you put all those questions
aside and says get this Arrow out
because I'll
die but the foolish man does not let the
doctor get the arrow out in other words
he doesn't do the gradual training here
and now to get the arrow out until he
has all these answers for just met why
and how and what led to this and how a
led to B and all of that and you real oh
yeah because those those views those
information that you collect provides
you sense of safety you find you derive
satisfaction from it to the point that
it it does actually alleviate suffering
you know somebody said something so
hurtful to you manage something somebody
something said so hurtful to you and
it's like you just it's just you don't
know how to deal with that pain but then
you find out that that person
was in pain they lost some and suddenly
you're not in pain it's like well you
haven't freed yourself from suffering
you just Managed IT exactly you just
changed its form but you remain equally
liable to somebody else saying something
hurtful so that means what every time
you need to find out what's your clan
why you shot me why didn't you shot
somebody else what did I do to you every
single time and you will run out of time
sooner or later you will run out of
time your view that things are permanent
makes you feel good you know like my you
don't want to think about it it's not an
explicit like oh I feel so much but it
it makes you feel that safety deep down
and that's exactly what what the Su says
what it says contemplate
change so you stop assuming permanence
in things that are there to you you stop
assuming that things won't change that's
it because no matter how satisfying a
thing is so say just keep it on on
family say attachment to family or
friend no matter how satisfying it is still
no matter how satisfying it is still
it's of the nature it's on the basis of
it is subject to change that's it nature
so can I is that satisfying that is
going to be taken away at any moment
well and that's the thing you don't need
to have your family taken away if you
contemplate subject to change in face of
things that you don't want to change
your emotionally invested for them not
changing you contemplate change you
realize your family would still remain
there yes you you don't need to get rid
of them you don't you don't need to have
them arrested or taken away What will
what will disappear is that layer of
satisfaction and kind of comfort that
you were finding in it that's that's the
only thing that would disappear but
obviously for
somebody who is not doing that practice
that is the that is the framework of
everything else everything they
experience in regard to their family and
so on is first through satisfaction
first through Comfort first through
ownership so that's that's why it's
scary to contemplate these things not
because thinking that your family is
subject to change will make it them
disappear this instant but it will make
your satisfaction and safety and
everything else built on it it will make
that disappear in an inst and then what
exactly then what am I left with yeah
nons satisfaction well then you're left
with the exra yeah and then you have a
choice as the people in the suas had a
choice okay either I will recognize this
and allow it to permeate my being
whereby I will not remain attached to
anything that requires my Gru's
Assumption of nonchanging because such
thing is not possible things will are
subject to change means eventually they
will be taken away that's the whole
point um
so so the only reason the only way
someone could suffer in regard to having
lost a something that they were attached
to e if they were finding satisfaction
satisfaction in that thing they weren't
seeing any
so then you can ask yourself like if
presumably you know person you read the
sutas you're familiar with you have some
ideas of anicha in practice so ask
yourself like do your ideas of
anicha do they make you feel anxious do
they make you feel like there's nothing
that you can find satisfaction and
safety in or do you not even feel any of
that everything just fits fits in place
just everything is neatly explained in
hindsight how everything happens and
it's all
fine and then see see which which one of
those is you basically and if you read
the suta that you just read you realize
which one you should
be because if those views of anicha were
right you will be free from any any see
any of satisfaction any any any um any
safety in the world any ownership if a
need is fully developed so and and CU
and also you can ask yourself like
um would you be free from assumptions
ownership Opanas uh finding satisfaction finding
Opanas uh finding satisfaction finding
safety in things would you be free from
all of that without needing to
constantly rehash and rehearse the
explanations that tell you how
everything happens so when things arise
are you free or do you have to tell
yourself nothing's real or do you have
to go through the emotions they then
free you from things that have Arisen
means you're not free you're just
managing that's
it so there I find I find something in
my life which I uh find satisfaction in
that is dear to me is I'm attached to
and then you contemplate that that thing
is subject to change yeah and you feel
anxxiety which means means you're attached
which means means you're attached
exactly so anxiety is not a problem as I
said so many times it's a symptom so if
you contemplate change in things that
you deem dear to you that you don't want
to change and you feel anxiety that
anxiety directly corresponds to the
amount to the to the degree of your
attachment towards those things to to
the degree of your gratuitous Assumption
of non-change so you realize okay so
anxiety shows me what I'm doing wrong
yeah I stop having those emotions
through diligent contemplation of
impermanence anxiety will disappear and
the diligent contemplation of
impermanence is not you going through
the random motions and so on it's
through allowing your thought that this will
allowing your thought that this will
change allowing it to endure not not
seeking to explain and get rid of it so
you find things that are there to you
then you contemplate that they will
change you think about it you reflect on
that then you have that anxiety and then
you leave that
enduring xiety in regard to your
thoughts of things that are dear to me
that I assume they will not change are
subject to change and just leave it and
even if the anxiety disappears you leave
that only when you get completely
distracted forget you bring it back
up I needed to qualify that because
people would think then oh so then I
just have to go through these mental
exercises and methods of just repeating
Mantra to myself that everything you got
to see and each exactly exactly exactly
you need to you need to get that sense
of oh this
is subject to change this is
unable everything that I'm everything
that exists from me in regard to it
ownership uh satisfaction all of that
all of that is contingent upon my
assumption of non-change of that thing
but I I have no control over it which
means my idea of non change is
ridiculous this is fully incapsulated in
its own nature that is subject to
change and let that endure let that
thought sit at the back of your mind
throughout your day that things are
subject to change nothing else and then
protect it through virtue and guarding
of the sense doors so you're not
distracted and fall back onto finding
satisfaction in things
grously you're being enamored with
things the lighting things that gets
removed that Withers away yeah that will
with away because you can't find the
light in something which is at it's cold
dangerous to you yeah to your well
that's the thing if if you're doing it
rightly through the Right View and
correct contemplation withering away of your um
contemplation withering away of your um
of your um sort of
intoxication with with life and things
that will be freeing the experience of
that will not be oh I'm depressed now
because there's nothing worth of my
satisfaction he will be no I'm free now
because there is nothing worth of me
finding safety in it and thus binding
myself to it and constricting my
mind uh but but if you are honest you
realize okay even if nothing's happening
now could I
suffer and what if I don't have the
ability or time to explain to myself why
and how
and all these things happen would I
suffer would I remain suffering what if
I refrain from engaging in retroactive
explanations of how my suffering came to
be and which is why I'm free now what if
I just as an experiment stop doing that
part and just let the suffering sit here
when it
arises would I would I would I be
touched by it would my mind be moved by
it or be completely completely above it
without any effort
needed but there is no amount of this
explanation that you can kind of install
in someone if they lack that Honesty on
that personal level of knowing what's
happening to
them and yeah simple again simple
question you can as I said you can quote
the commentary and you can say this and
everything is kapas are constantly
moving and all this but that's not how
you see
things like is your Consciousness
constantly moving is your life
constantly flickering on and off on and
off on like that makes no sense and if
you never heard that external view that
you're now kind of trying to to fit the
sutas with and so on it would have never
crossed your mind to describe your
experience like that because that's not
what your experience
is putting aside the whole thing that if
you think you can measure motions of
durations of your Consciousness in
moments and flickering like what
commentaries and the whole kind of
contemporary and bur is person think
that would require you to to be
basically be an observer outside of this
experience as a whole to measure that
change but you can't do that you can't
even imagine the outside of the five
Aggregates as the Buddha said so many
times yeah you're fully enclosed so
there is no outside point of view for
you in regard to yourself s not
others it's the aggregate to form
feeling perception intention and
Consciousness fully
encapsulated so these Notions of
measuring I remember I read that it was
this um the storage of Consciousness the
collect it's like how can you even know
that when all you have is your own
consciousness of
phenomena but you come across these
ideas these phenomenas and then you
ascribe this external value or this
precedes me this is the greater
Consciousness over there or or the view
I think also it was in one of the the
early commentaries where where the uh
moment to moment Consciousness which
again it's just an external idea uh
these moments last like 0.0 something as
milliseconds and it's was like how can
you measure that how can you measure
your own Consciousness or how can you
measure someone else's flicking Moments
Of Consciousness that's insane that's
fantasy yeah but even you say you you could see
yeah but even you say you you could see
these moment to moment you cannot see
them in that external sense you are them
your observation of it your experience
as a whole your intention to look at
these moments remains there enduring for
all this
time your intention to manage your
suffering and refuse to allow duka to
endure remains their enduring as a basis
for all of your other little views that
flicker left and right as you read this
or you read
that so that's what the honesty has to
bring you back to that recognition of
liability to suffer and where your
intentions are and your intentions are
not constantly changing if they were you
would not be able to intend anything let
alone act towards anything they are the
the glue The Binding factor that unifies
your particular actions that sure they
are changing they're fast because they
have a greater context that remains
unchanged which is why you're still
doing this which is why I'm still
sitting here talking answering questions
and so on
so what is the way that one sees
things uh experiences
things but you know
just without going into beliefs and just
you know from the start you just here
you are just here well experien stuff I
don't yeah I mean like you you're going
to have some
input so if you just just if you dismiss
any information in regard to how you're
experiencing things then you're just
going to mystify it I'm just here and
the nness and the isness and the what
whatness so either
way you are not neutral when it comes to
your experience so the question is
finding the right
information and that's the point here
all of this is the information that
shows you the contradiction of the other
information the management the how it
doesn't add up how you cannot possibly
see yourself in the external sense from
which you can measure your own
Consciousness duration and all of that
because of that you abandon that
information and then you find but you
need information one of the factors for
the right view is the utterance of
another rightly
understood but yes you have people say
oh this information is just causing
confusion it's just too much so they
dismiss all information they don't want
to read the suits yes
sure part of it resulted in good CU they
dismissed all the wrong information all
the commentaries all the V passers all
the modern stuff that's being taught but
then they also dismiss the right
information so what they're left with
then is the the complete mystification
of whatever's here because you don't
have the means to understand it by
yourself if you did well you would be
some somew but you have so you have to
somew but you have so you have to
develop you have to develop some view
you have to develop the Right View yeah
you have to develop Right View you
already have views yeah you're not View
without any views or standpoints but you
need to develop the right view the right
standpoint that then correctly without
perversion represents your
experience but your experience is is
always going to be known through views
so that's why then you
realize with that honest transparency
that if I truly want to be free from
suffering then I need to find the
teaching that does not provide another
explanation for what's happening to me
and another belief and another kind of
oh this is how it is and that's it adopt
this and you're fine because everything
fits no I need to find instructions that
will make me
basically not be able to experience
suffering in the first place and then if
you take that view already see that's
already like a right view for a PJ
because he already knows where to look
so then that person would then it would
not be too farfetched to then see how
virtue Taming of the senses Solitude how
is that fortifying your mind you realize
oh it's not about just another
explanation just another belief it's
about training and undoing this being
here that when touched by feeling It
suffers it resists it wants more and all
of that so it's it's it's
dismantling those reactions those those
habits those basically assumptions in
regard to that and you oh yeah how would
you start well by
taming by by constricting the wrong
Behavior by taming by moderating eating
by speech by all of that and then the
Mind becomes
immovable and then you get to see these
things and then you oh yeah when you
understood then that whatever touches
you whatever it's manifested that's why
it's impermanent because it came on its
own not because you saw it ending or
because this or you explained it and
then I don't need to do anything for as
long as I'm alive anything that I
experience I will be reminded of my
freedom from it through that experience
so this is a su from
theay and this
is where King Maha suasana is passing
away and he's the queen visits him on
his deathbed and she says sa you have 84,000
deathbed and she says sa you have 84,000
cities with royal capital of kavati
foremost arouse desire for these take an
interest in life all these wonderful
things that you have and he's got all
possessions all these possessions got
everything and he rules with kindness
and what and she likewise urged the king to
what and she likewise urged the king to
live on by taking an interest in all his
possessions as described above Army and
horses and pales and wives jewels of
everything yeah wealth yeah and when the
queen had spoken the king said to her
for a long time my queen you have spoken
to me with loving desirable Pleasant and
agreeable words and yet in my final hour
your words are undesirable unpleasant
and disagreeable then she said to him then
disagreeable then she said to him then
how exactly your majesty am I to speak
to you and he says like this my queen s
we must be parted and separated from all
we hold dear and beloved don't pass away
with concerns such concern is suffering
and it is criticized say you have 84,000
cities with the Royal capital of kavati
foremost give up desire for these take
no interest in life yeah and so for all
of the king's possession before the life
ends which you still holding on to them
exactly that's there's a suffering there
so when the king had spoken Queen the
queen cried started to C burst into
tears wiping away her tears the queen
said to the king she said what he told
her to say so on and at the at the end
of that that
Sut the Buddha goes on to say that
famous verse all determinations all conditions
verse all determinations all conditions
are impermanent all determinations are
impermanent their nature is to arise and
cease having aison they will have to
cease they will have to come to end
their stealing is true Bliss they
stealing not their
sensation they stealing yeah stealing of
them while they're there that's the
point so before things have ceased for
that King I before he died before things
were ripped
away he's advising himself through the
queen to abandon desire towards those
determinations towards those
possessions to steal them to let them be
so to speak to remove his emotional
involvement ownership satisfaction
safety and everything else because if
that's not done there is no so then the
point is like okay so do you practicing
stealing of your ownership or do you
just sort of uh trying to to kind of
inject The View that nothing is
permanent because it will it will
disappear that's not stealing that's
just another
sensation so you want to steal things
before they
cease stealing of Saras is the peace is
the Bliss is nibana not cessation of
them because that's still some
s they cease here they rise somewhere
else
so again even that whole suta rests the
whole notion of anicha the whole notion
of impermanence on the level of
possessions on the level of things that
you desire they provide satisfaction
they provide Zeal inspiration will to
live so you're stealing that desire
you're not denying the reality and the
existence of those things through your
secondary hindsight um contrived explanations